<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>AD&#39;s Logs</title>
  
  
  <link href="https://0xakd.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  
  <link href="https://0xakd.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2025-07-19T11:21:34.466Z</updated>
  <id>https://0xakd.github.io/</id>
  
  <author>
    <name>Ajay Kumar Dey</name>
    
  </author>
  
  <generator uri="https://hexo.io/">Hexo</generator>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Dynamic Memory Allocation in C</title>
    <link href="https://0xakd.github.io/2025/07/19/dynamic-memory-allocation-in-c/"/>
    <id>https://0xakd.github.io/2025/07/19/dynamic-memory-allocation-in-c/</id>
    <published>2025-07-19T11:21:34.000Z</published>
    <updated>2025-07-19T11:21:34.466Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/../images/dynamic-memory-allocation-in-c/coverpage.jpeg" alt="cover pic"></p><h2 id="Dynamic-Memory-Allocation-in-C"><a href="#Dynamic-Memory-Allocation-in-C" class="headerlink" title="Dynamic Memory Allocation in C"></a>Dynamic Memory Allocation in C</h2><p>Before jumping to Dynamic memory allocation we need to know about how the memory is used by a program in C.</p><p>There are 4 memory segments :-</p><ul><li><p><strong>Stack</strong> - it is a region of limited amount of memory that is temporary allocated to a program by the processor and the compiler</p><ul><li>It operates in LIFO (Last in first out) format. That means that the last piece of data added to the stack is the first one to be removed.</li><li>The stack is mainly used for storing local variables, function parameters and return addresses.</li></ul></li><li><p><strong>Heap</strong> - It is a region of memory which is used for dynamic memory allocation.</p><ul><li>this allows more flexible memory usage, as its size is much larger than stack. So the memory can be allocated and freed in any order.</li><li>The heap is used for variables that need to persist beyond the scope of a function or for large data structures that exceed the stack’s capacity.</li></ul></li><li><p><strong>Static&#x2F;Global</strong>- The static and Global variables are stored in this part..</p></li><li><p><strong>Code</strong> - This part of memory stores the executable code of the program.</p></li></ul><p><img src="/../images/dynamic-memory-allocation-in-c/image2.jpeg" alt="Application memory"></p><h3 id="Now-back-to-Dynamic-memory-allocation…"><a href="#Now-back-to-Dynamic-memory-allocation…" class="headerlink" title="Now back to Dynamic memory allocation…"></a>Now back to Dynamic memory allocation…</h3><p>Dynamic memory allocation refers to the process of dynamically allocating memory during runtime of a program, rather than at compile-time, i.e. static memory allocation.</p><p>By default, a limited amount of memory is allocated to a program. The default Memory allocation differs every time. It is decided by the processor and the compiler that how much memory should be allocated to a program.</p><p>In C language, Dynamic memory allocation can be done by the following functions which are present in the &lt;stdlib.h&gt; header file.-</p><ul><li><p><strong>malloc() -</strong></p><ul><li><p>it stands for “Memory Allocation”.</p></li><li><p>This function is used to dynamically allocate a block of memory of specified size from the heap and returns a pointer to the address of the first byte of the allocated memory in the stack.</p></li><li><p>The memory allocated using malloc() function remains in the heap untill its manually freed with the free() function.</p></li><li><p>In case, if the malloc() function is unable to allocate memory it will return NULL.</p></li></ul></li><li><p><strong>calloc() -</strong> </p><ul><li><p>It stands for “Clear Allocation”.</p></li><li><p>The calloc() function is similar as the malloc() function, but with a additional feature of initializing the allocated memory block to zero.</p></li><li><p>This function is commonly used when initializing arrays or structures to avoid unpredictable behavior caused by uninitialized values.</p></li></ul></li><li><p><strong>realloc() -</strong></p><ul><li><p>It stands for “Reallocate”.</p></li><li><p>It is used to resize of memory block that was previously allocated using malloc() or calloc() functions.</p></li><li><p>If there is enough space to expand the block, the realloc() function will adjust the size of the block and return a pointer to the new memory. If there is not enough space, the function may allocate a new block of the requested size, copy the contents of the old block to the new block, and free the old block.</p></li></ul></li><li><p><strong>free() -</strong></p><ul><li><p>This function is used to deallocate memory that was previously allocated using either malloc(), calloc(), or realloc().</p></li><li><p>If a program attempts to access freed memory, it can result in undefined behavior, including crashes and unexpected results.</p></li></ul></li></ul><p>Syntax of the above functions…<br><img src="/../images/dynamic-memory-allocation-in-c/image.png" alt="functions syntax"></p>]]></content>
    
    
      
      
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/../images/dynamic-memory-allocation-in-c/coverpage.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;cover pic&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;Dynamic-Memory-Allocation-in-C&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=</summary>
      
    
    
    
    <category term="programming" scheme="https://0xakd.github.io/categories/programming/"/>
    
    <category term="software" scheme="https://0xakd.github.io/categories/programming/software/"/>
    
    
    <category term="C" scheme="https://0xakd.github.io/tags/C/"/>
    
    <category term="dynamic-memory-allocation" scheme="https://0xakd.github.io/tags/dynamic-memory-allocation/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Arduino for the Clueless (but Curious)</title>
    <link href="https://0xakd.github.io/2025/07/17/Arduino-for-the-Clueless-but-Curious/"/>
    <id>https://0xakd.github.io/2025/07/17/Arduino-for-the-Clueless-but-Curious/</id>
    <published>2025-07-17T13:12:26.000Z</published>
    <updated>2025-07-19T11:08:19.611Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/../images/Arduino-for-the-Clueless-but-Curious/coverpage.jpeg" alt="cover page"></p><blockquote><p>“Ever wished you could build your own robot or control lights with just a few lines of code?”</p></blockquote><p>Arduino lets anyone try electronics, even if you’ve never done it before. The parts are easy to use, and the software is simple.</p><p>You don’t need to be a coding genius to start. If you’ve ever plugged in a USB cable or built a LEGO set, you’re already qualified to start.</p><hr><h2 id="What-is-Arduino"><a href="#What-is-Arduino" class="headerlink" title="What is Arduino???"></a>What is Arduino???</h2><p>Arduino is an italian open-source electronics platform based on easy-to-use hardware and software. Arduino consists of both a physical programmable circuit board (often referred to as a microcontroller) and a piece of software or IDE (Integrated Development Environment) that runs on your computer, used to write and upload code to the physical board. </p><p><img src="/../images/Arduino-for-the-Clueless-but-Curious/labeledboard.jpeg" alt="Arduino Board"> </p><center><i>This is an Arduino Uno Board</i></center><hr><h3 id="What’s-on-the-Arduino-Board"><a href="#What’s-on-the-Arduino-Board" class="headerlink" title="What’s on the Arduino Board??"></a>What’s on the Arduino Board??</h3><ul><li><p><strong>Pins</strong><br>The Arduino board is equipped with a variety of pins that serve different purposes in connecting and controlling electronic components.</p><ol><li><strong>Digital Pins:</strong> There are 14 digital pins (numbered 0–13) on the Arduino board. These pins can read or write digital signals—either HIGH (on) or LOW (off)—to and from connected devices.</li><li><strong>PWM Pins:</strong> Out of the digital pins, 6 are PWM (Pulse Width Modulation) pins, marked with a tilde (~). PWM pins allow you to simulate analog output by varying the signal between 0 and 255, useful for controlling things like LED brightness or motor speed.</li><li><strong>Analog Input Pins:</strong> The board includes 6 analog input pins (A0–A5). These pins can read a range of voltage values, letting you capture sensor data with greater precision (values from 0 to 1023).</li><li><strong>Power Pins:</strong> These pins supply voltage (3.3V or 5V) and ground (GND) connections to power external components and sensors.</li><li><strong>Communication Pins:</strong> The board also features pins for serial communication, such as TX (transmit) and RX (receive), which are used to communicate with your computer or other devices.</li><li><strong>GND Pins:</strong> These are the ‘Ground’ pins. The Arduino board has 3 GND pins, and any of them can be used to complete the circuit by providing a common ground connection.</li></ol></li><li><p><strong>Reset Button</strong><br>  The Arduino reset button is a Physical button on the board, which is when pressed, causes the microcontroller to temporarily connect the reset pin to the ground and restart any code that is loaded on the Arduino.</p></li><li><p><strong>USB Type B Port</strong><br>  The USB Type B port is used to connect the Arduino board to your computer. This connection serves two purposes: it powers the board and allows you to upload code from the Arduino IDE to the microcontroller.</p></li><li><p><strong>Power Jack</strong><br>  The power jack allows you to supply external power to the Arduino board, typically using a 7–12V DC adapter. This is useful when your project requires more power than what the USB connection can provide, or when you want your Arduino to run independently of your computer.</p></li><li><p><strong>ATMEGA328P Microcontroller</strong><br>  The ATMEGA328P microcontroller is the brain of the Arduino board. It stores and executes the code uploaded from the Arduino IDE, manages all inputs and outputs, and handles logic and timing for your projects.</p></li><li><p><strong>ICSP Pins</strong><br>  These are ICSP(In-Circuit Serial Programming) Pins. These pins are mainly used for low-level programming of the microcontrollers, like burning the bootloader or uploading firmware.</p></li></ul><hr><h3 id="Arduino-IDE"><a href="#Arduino-IDE" class="headerlink" title="Arduino IDE"></a>Arduino IDE</h3><p>The Arduino IDE (Integrated Development Environment) is an open-source software written in Java that runs on multiple platforms including Windows, macOS, and Linux. It serves as the primary tool for writing, compiling, and uploading code to Arduino boards.</p><p>Just like other code editors, the Arduino IDE provides a user-friendly interface with features like syntax highlighting, auto-indentation, and error messaging, which make writing code easier even for beginners. One of its biggest advantages is the simplicity — you can write your code (called a “sketch”) and upload it to your Arduino board with just a single click.</p><p>You can download the IDE from the <strong><a href="https://www.arduino.cc/en/software">official Arduino website</a></strong>, and it’s completely free to use.</p><p><img src="/../images/Arduino-for-the-Clueless-but-Curious/arduino_ide.jpeg" alt="Arduino IDE"></p><center><i>Screenshot of Arduino IDE.</i></center><br><h3 id="Components-of-the-Arduino-IDE"><a href="#Components-of-the-Arduino-IDE" class="headerlink" title="Components of the Arduino IDE"></a>Components of the Arduino IDE</h3><p>Let’s now talk about the main components of the IDE interface that you’ll interact with:</p><ul><li><strong>Toolbar</strong>: Includes buttons to verify, upload, create a new sketch, open, save, and more.</li><li><strong>Text Editor</strong>: Where you write your code (sketch).</li><li><strong>Message Area</strong>: Displays compiler errors and notifications.</li><li><strong>Console</strong>: Shows detailed output like errors and upload status.</li><li><strong>Board &amp; Port Selector</strong>: Lets you choose the connected Arduino board and COM port.</li><li><strong>Serial Monitor</strong>: A powerful built-in tool used to send and receive data from your Arduino in real time.</li></ul><h3 id="The-Serial-Monitor"><a href="#The-Serial-Monitor" class="headerlink" title="The Serial Monitor"></a>The Serial Monitor</h3><p>The <strong>Serial Monitor</strong> is an essential debugging tool in the Arduino IDE. It allows you to print messages, read sensor outputs, and interact with the Arduino through serial communication.</p><p>For example, if you write:</p><figure class="highlight cpp"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><span class="line">Serial.<span class="built_in">begin</span>(<span class="number">9600</span>);</span><br><span class="line">Serial.<span class="built_in">println</span>(<span class="string">&quot;Hello World&quot;</span>);</span><br><span class="line"></span><br></pre></td></tr></table></figure><p><img src="/../images/Arduino-for-the-Clueless-but-Curious/serial_monitor.jpeg" alt="Arduino Serial Monitor"></p><center><i>Screenshot of Arduino Serial Monitor</i></center><h3 id="Real-World-Applications-Of-Arduino"><a href="#Real-World-Applications-Of-Arduino" class="headerlink" title="Real World Applications Of Arduino"></a>Real World Applications Of Arduino</h3><p>Arduino is used in countless real-world applications, from simple hobby projects to advanced . You’ll find Arduino boards powering home automation systems, weather stations, wearable devices, interactive art installations, robotics, and even scientific instruments. Its versatility and ease of use make it a favorite among students, engineers, artists, and makers worldwide.</p><h2 id="Components-You-Need-to-Get-Started"><a href="#Components-You-Need-to-Get-Started" class="headerlink" title="Components You Need to Get Started"></a>Components You Need to Get Started</h2><ul><li><strong>Arduino Uno Board</strong></li><li><strong>USB Type B Cable</strong></li><li><strong>Bread Board</strong></li><li><strong>LEDs, resistors, jumper wires, potentiometer</strong></li><li><strong>Sensors</strong></li><li><strong>Computer with Arduino IDE installed.</strong></li></ul><p>If you don’t have the physical components right now, you can use the <strong><a href="https://www.tinkercad.com/">Tinkercad</a></strong> website to get started. It provides a graphical simulation environment where you can build circuits, write Arduino code, and test your projects virtually — all from your browser. Tinkercad also includes a built-in Arduino IDE and a Serial Monitor, allowing you to write and debug your code just like on the actual Arduino software.</p><h2 id="How-Arduino-Code-Talks-to-the-Hardware"><a href="#How-Arduino-Code-Talks-to-the-Hardware" class="headerlink" title="How Arduino Code Talks to the Hardware"></a>How Arduino Code Talks to the Hardware</h2><p>Programming Arduino is done using a simplified version of C&#x2F;C++. The code you write is called a “sketch.” Every sketch has two main functions:</p><figure class="highlight cpp"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br><span class="line">4</span><br><span class="line">5</span><br><span class="line">6</span><br><span class="line">7</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><span class="line"><span class="function"><span class="type">void</span> <span class="title">setup</span><span class="params">()</span> </span>&#123;</span><br><span class="line">    <span class="comment">// Runs once when the board is powered on or reset</span></span><br><span class="line">&#125;</span><br><span class="line"></span><br><span class="line"><span class="function"><span class="type">void</span> <span class="title">loop</span><span class="params">()</span> </span>&#123;</span><br><span class="line">    <span class="comment">// Runs repeatedly after setup()</span></span><br><span class="line">&#125;</span><br></pre></td></tr></table></figure><ul><li><strong>setup()</strong>: Used to initialize settings, such as configuring pin modes or starting serial communication.</li><li><strong>loop()</strong>: Contains the main logic and runs continuously.</li></ul><h3 id="Example-Blink-an-LED"><a href="#Example-Blink-an-LED" class="headerlink" title="Example: Blink an LED"></a>Example: Blink an LED</h3><p>This classic example turns an LED on and off every second.</p><figure class="highlight cpp"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br><span class="line">4</span><br><span class="line">5</span><br><span class="line">6</span><br><span class="line">7</span><br><span class="line">8</span><br><span class="line">9</span><br><span class="line">10</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><span class="line"><span class="function"><span class="type">void</span> <span class="title">setup</span><span class="params">()</span> </span>&#123;</span><br><span class="line">    <span class="built_in">pinMode</span>(<span class="number">13</span>, OUTPUT); <span class="comment">// Set digital pin 13 as output mode</span></span><br><span class="line">&#125;</span><br><span class="line"></span><br><span class="line"><span class="function"><span class="type">void</span> <span class="title">loop</span><span class="params">()</span> </span>&#123;</span><br><span class="line">    <span class="built_in">digitalWrite</span>(<span class="number">13</span>, HIGH); <span class="comment">// Turn the LED on</span></span><br><span class="line">    <span class="built_in">delay</span>(<span class="number">1000</span>);            <span class="comment">// Wait 1 second</span></span><br><span class="line">    <span class="built_in">digitalWrite</span>(<span class="number">13</span>, LOW);  <span class="comment">// Turn the LED off</span></span><br><span class="line">    <span class="built_in">delay</span>(<span class="number">1000</span>);            <span class="comment">// Wait 1 second</span></span><br><span class="line">&#125;</span><br></pre></td></tr></table></figure><p>Before uploading your code to the Arduino, let’s first build the circuit.</p><p><img src="/../images/Arduino-for-the-Clueless-but-Curious/ledcircuit.png" alt="LED Blink Circuit"></p><center><i>Circuit for Blinking LED</i></center><p>Once your circuit is ready, connect your Arduino to your computer. In the Arduino IDE, select the correct board type and COM port from the Tools menu. Click the “Upload” button to transfer your sketch to the Arduino. If everything is set up correctly, the built-in LED on pin 13 will start blinking on and off each second.</p><h3 id="Key-Functions"><a href="#Key-Functions" class="headerlink" title="Key Functions"></a>Key Functions</h3><ul><li><code>pinMode(pin_number, mode)</code>: Sets a pin as INPUT or OUTPUT.</li><li><code>digitalWrite(pin_number, value)</code>: Sets a digital pin HIGH or LOW.</li><li><code>digitalRead(pin_number)</code>: Reads the value from a digital pin.</li><li><code>analogRead(pin_number)</code>: Reads an analog value (0–1023).</li><li><code>analogWrite(pin_number, value)</code>: Writes an analog value (PWM, 0–255).</li></ul><p>Experiment with different sensors and actuators by changing the code and wiring. The Arduino IDE provides many built-in examples to help you learn.</p><hr><h2 id="Conclusion"><a href="#Conclusion" class="headerlink" title="Conclusion"></a>Conclusion</h2><p>Arduino makes electronics and programming accessible to everyone, regardless of background or experience. With just a few components and simple code, you can start building interactive projects and learn valuable skills along the way. Whether you want to automate your home, create art, or explore robotics, Arduino is the perfect platform to turn your curiosity into real-world creations. Dive in, experiment, and let your imagination lead the way!</p><hr><h2 id="Further-Resources"><a href="#Further-Resources" class="headerlink" title="Further Resources"></a>Further Resources</h2><p>To deepen your understanding and expand your skills, consider exploring the following resources:</p><ul><li><strong>Official Arduino Documentation:</strong> Comprehensive guides and reference materials — <a href="https://docs.arduino.cc/">Arduino Docs</a></li><li><strong>Arduino Project Hub:</strong> Browse and contribute to a wide range of community projects — <a href="https://arduino.cc/projecthub">Project Hub</a></li><li><strong>Online Courses:</strong> Platforms like Coursera, Udemy, and edX offer structured Arduino courses for all levels.</li><li><strong>Community Forums:</strong> Engage with other makers, ask questions, and share your progress — <a href="https://forum.arduino.cc/">Arduino Forum</a></li></ul><p>Investing time in these resources will help you build a strong foundation and stay updated with the latest advancements in Arduino and embedded systems.</p>]]></content>
    
    
      
      
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/../images/Arduino-for-the-Clueless-but-Curious/coverpage.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;cover page&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Ever wished you could bu</summary>
      
    
    
    
    <category term="electronics" scheme="https://0xakd.github.io/categories/electronics/"/>
    
    <category term="embedded-systems" scheme="https://0xakd.github.io/categories/electronics/embedded-systems/"/>
    
    <category term="hardware" scheme="https://0xakd.github.io/categories/electronics/embedded-systems/hardware/"/>
    
    
    <category term="arduino" scheme="https://0xakd.github.io/tags/arduino/"/>
    
    <category term="basics" scheme="https://0xakd.github.io/tags/basics/"/>
    
    <category term="DIY" scheme="https://0xakd.github.io/tags/DIY/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
</feed>
